<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Jean-Denis | Beaudoin Lab</title>
    <link>https://beaudoinlab.org/authors/jean-denis/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://beaudoinlab.org/authors/jean-denis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Jean-Denis</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2019  Daniel Burkhardt</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://beaudoinlab.org/img/social-card.jpg</url>
      <title>Jean-Denis</title>
      <link>https://beaudoinlab.org/authors/jean-denis/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>An example preprint / working paper</title>
      <link>https://beaudoinlab.org/news/new-article/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://beaudoinlab.org/news/new-article/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Click the &lt;em&gt;Slides&lt;/em&gt; button above to demo Academic&amp;rsquo;s Markdown slides feature.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supplementary notes can be added here, including &lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;code and math&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An example journal article</title>
      <link>https://beaudoinlab.org/news/journal-article/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://beaudoinlab.org/news/journal-article/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Click the &lt;em&gt;Cite&lt;/em&gt; button above to demo the feature to enable visitors to import publication metadata into their reference management software.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Click the &lt;em&gt;Slides&lt;/em&gt; button above to demo Academic&amp;rsquo;s Markdown slides feature.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supplementary notes can be added here, including &lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;code and math&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An example conference paper</title>
      <link>https://beaudoinlab.org/news/conference-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://beaudoinlab.org/news/conference-paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Click the &lt;em&gt;Cite&lt;/em&gt; button above to demo the feature to enable visitors to import publication metadata into their reference management software.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Click the &lt;em&gt;Slides&lt;/em&gt; button above to demo Academic&amp;rsquo;s Markdown slides feature.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supplementary notes can be added here, including &lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;code and math&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jean-Denis</title>
      <link>https://beaudoinlab.org/authors/jean-denis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://beaudoinlab.org/authors/jean-denis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hi! I am Jean-Denis, a French Canadian who came to the US to complete his Post-doctoral studies at Yale University and who is now joining the UCONN Health team as an Assistant Professor! Here is a little bit about myself. Curiously, I fit most Canadian stereotypes out there. I don’t qualify winter in Connecticut as real winter. I need to play hockey to stay mentally sane. I provide maple syrup to people from the department in the Spring and I love lumberjacking with my grandfather in the Fall. You will see me wearing Montreal Canadiens gears on important game days, but I much prefer American football over Canadian football. When I am not in the lab, I enjoy passing quality time with my family. I have a young son and watching him grow is simply sublime. I am a big craft beer amateur and will venture to new breweries all over the northeast on weekends. I stay connected with the outdoors by hiking, skiing, ice skating, snowshoeing, rollerblading, fishing and more. In short, I practice a good balance between personal and professional life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Professionally, I am a very enthusiastic person. I love to share my passion for science with others and discuss about new ideas, experiments, results, recent publications, meetings and more. I completed my B.Sc. in Biotechnology at Université de Sherbrooke (Québec, Canada) and my Ph.D. in Biochemistry in the laboratory of Jean-Pierre Perreault at Université de Sherbrooke (Québec Canada). During my graduate studies, I addressed how do RNA structures control RNA activity? My work discovered novel properties and functions of RNA G-quadruplexes, a structure formed by G-rich sequences. First, I characterized their folding properties and dynamics in vitro (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18456841&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Beaudoin JD, &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt; 2008&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&#34;ttps://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23500045&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Beaudoin JD, &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt; 2013&lt;/a&gt;). Next, I developed an algorithm to locate genomic sequences susceptible to form G-quaruplexes (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24121682&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Beaudoin JD,  &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt; 2014&lt;/a&gt;) and found that, in human cell cultures, 5’-UTR G-quadruplexes act as key translational repressors (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20571090&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Beaudoin JD and Perreault JP, 2010&lt;/a&gt;) and 3’-UTR G-quadruplexes can modulate alternative polyadenylation leading to differential expression (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23609544&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Beaudoin JD. and Perreault JP., Nucleic Acids Res. 2013&lt;/a&gt;). Together, this work provided mechanistic insights into a previously unrecognized role for RNA G-quadruplexes in gene expression regulation. Following from this work, we developed an oligonucleotide-based approach to target individual RNA G-quadruplexes and tune gene expression in a desired direction (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/25510493&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Rouleau SG, Beaudoin JD, &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt; 2015&lt;/a&gt;). These findings highlighted the potential to target RNA regulatory elements to control gene expression, opening promising novel therapeutic strategies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2013, I started my postdoc in the laboratory of Antonio Giraldez at Yale University. For my postdoctoral work, I extended my expertise in molecular, cellular and RNA biology to study a fundamental process in all animals, the maternal-to-zygotic transition, where post-transcriptional regulation orchestrates a profound change in the embryonic transcriptional landscape. Here, I asked two central questions: what are the RNA structures formed during early embryogenesis and how do they interact with cellular factors to control gene expression during development? To address these questions, I developed innovative genome-wide in vivo RNA probing techniques to gain structural information on the zebrafish transcriptome during embryogenesis. I also expanded my technical repertoire to perform high throughput approaches to measure genome-wide gene expression in vivo, including mRNA abundance (RNA-seq) and translation (Ribo-seq). By integrating this information, I generated a global interaction map between RNA structure, mRNA stability and translation during early embryogenesis (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/30061596&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Beaudoin JD*, Novoa EM* &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt; 2018.&lt;/a&gt;). Our results provide three major insights: (1) Contrary to the current dogma, we found that untranslated mRNAs are more structured in vivo compared to in vitro, (2) globally, translation guides mRNA structures rather than structure guiding translation (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/30061597&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Karmer MC and Gregory BD, 2018.&lt;/a&gt;), and (3) RNA structures remodeled in 3’-UTRs are enriched for regulatory activity during development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I am extremely excited to start my lab at UConn Health in the Department of Genetics and Genome Sciences and can’t wait to see what the future holds!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
